Wormley Family 065
People's Archive, MLK Library
Wormley Family Genealogical Research Collection
1784-1984
People's Archive, MLK Library
Wormley family
065
4.5 Linear feet
Arrangement
Series 1: Miscellaneous Information Series 2: Individuals and Family Groups Series 3: Genealogical Information and Charts Series 4: Photographs Series 5: Supplemental Volumes
Biographical / Historical
The Wormley family of Washington, D.C. is one of the most notable African American families in the history of the District of Columbia. Most notable among the family members are, James Wormley, proprietor of the Wormley Hotel, and Stanton L. Wormley, Sr., former interim President of Howard University. James Wormley was born free in 1819 in Washington, D.C. His parents, Lynch and Mary Wormley, came to the District from Virginia in 1814 and established a carriage business. In 1871, James Wormley established the Wormley Hotel on the corner of 15th and H Streets, NW. This was the site of the "Wormley Agreement," the name given to the Compromise of 1877 that ended the presidential disputed election of 1876 and, with the selection of Rutherford B. Hayes as President, also ended Reconstruction in the South. Wormley was also instrumental in making sure that Congress provided appropriate funding to the D.C. public schools. Stanton L. Wormley, Sr. was born in Washington, D.C. in 1909. He attended Howard University and was a member of the ROTC and the Glee Club. Stanton, Sr. also studied in Germany and was the leader of the Virginia State Glee Club. He then became a member of the faculty at Howard University and, in 1965, was eventually named interim President after University President James M. Nabrit, Jr. was appointed U.S. Representative to the United Nations by President Lyndon B. Johnson. There are many members of note in the Wormley family, as well as those who married into the family. Among these are Francis L. Cardozo, former Secretary of State and state treasurer of South Carolina, and a leader in the public schools of Washington, D.C., including principal of present-day Paul Laurence Dunbar High School.
Custodial History
Members of the Wormley family compiled this collection including: Stanton L. Wormley, Sr., Stanton L. Wormley, Jr. and Paul E. Sluby, Sr. Each volume was originally housed in a photo album or binder. The items were transferred to the Library in April 2006.
Related Materials
Copies of the materials in this collection can be found at the Virginia State Library Library of Virginia in Richmond, Virginia and with the Stanton L. Wormley, Jr. family. Cleveland ( Ohio) Public Library, African-American Family Photograph Collection: The Wormley/Graves Photograph Collection, 1930-1979.
Scope and Contents
The collection was organized by the Wormley family before it was transferred to the Library. An index was published and included in the collection. Therefore, it was decided that the collection maintain its original order. However, there are volumes listed in the index that are not present in the collection. Included with the collection are three CD-ROM discs that contain scanned images of the volumes. However, these discs are not complete. Several items are missing from the files of various volumes. The collection consists of genealogical and historical materials on the Wormley family. Materials include slave data, census records, wills, deeds, interviews, articles, and photographs.
Genealogy; Photographs; African Americans; Families; Black persons
- Series 1: Miscellaneous Information
  - Index to the Wormley Family Papers [bound volume], Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Wormley and Shadd City Directory Information - Wormley Birth and Death Certificates, Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Wormley and Shadd City Directory Information - Wormley Birth and Death Certificates, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Wormley and Burruss Personal Interviews, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Wormley and Shadd Marriage - Wills, 1828-1965 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Wormley and Shadd Marriage - Wills/Estates, 1828-1965 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Wormley Property Transfers, Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Members of the Wormley Family mentioned in the Minutes of the Berean Baptist Church and the 15th Street Presbyterian Church, 1878-1898 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Wormley Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Wormley Source Materials, Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Wormley Family Genealogy Volumes 001-073, Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Series 2: Individuals and Family Groups
  - Wormley Beginnings and Rosegill - Charts 1312-1726, 1812-1852 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Wormley Beginnings and Rosegill Volume 1, 1850 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Wormley Beginnings and Rosegill Volume 2, 1850 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Wormley Beginnings and Rosegill Volume 3, 1850-1853 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Wormley Beginnings and Rosegill Volume 4, Undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Wormley Beginnings and Rosegill Volume 5, Undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Wormley Family of Virginia - 17th and 18th Centuries Volume 1, Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Wormley Family of Virginia - 17th and 18th Centuries Volume 2, Undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Wormley Family of Virginia - 17th and 18th Centuries Volume 3, Undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Wormley Family of Virginia - 17th and 18th Centuries Volume 4, Undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Wormley Family of Virginia - 17th and 18th Centuries Volume 5, Undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Wormley General Information Volume 1, Undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Wormley General Information Volume 2, Undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Lynch Wormley, 1784-1850 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Family of Lynch Wormley, 1830-1882 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - James Wormley, Volume 1, Undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - James Wormley, Volume 2, Undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - James Wormley, Volume 3, Undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Mary M. Wormley, Undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - William H. A. Wormley, 1875-1977 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Letters of William H. A. Wormley, 1860-1967 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Family of William H. A. Wormley, 1897-1962 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Miriam Wormley Lewis, 1910-1980 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Family of James Thompson Wormley, Undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Family of Garrett Smith Wormley, 1885-1981 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Lawrence R. Wormley Volume 1, 1904-1951 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Lawrence R. Wormley Volume 2, 1952-1962 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Mary E. (Burruss) Wormley, 1885-1938 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Burruss Family - Family of Mary E. (Burruss) Wormley, 1840-1980 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Stanton L. Wormley, Sr. Volume 1, 1909-1932 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Stanton L. Wormley, Sr. Volume 2, 1933-1954 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Stanton L. Wormley, Sr. Volume 3, 1954-1966 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Stanton L. Wormley, Sr. Volume 4, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Stanton L. Wormley, Sr. Volume 5, 1967-1979 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Stanton L. Wormley, Sr. - Miscellaneous Volume 6, 1964-1981 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Howard Glee Club Volume 1 (also includes photograph), 1929-1931 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Howard Glee Club Volume 2, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Virginia State Glee Club Volume 1 (also includes photograph), 1933-1934 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Virginia State Glee Club Volume 2 (also includes photograph), 1934-1937 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Stanton L. Wormley - Sr. Publications, 1937-1969 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Shadd Family Volume 1, Undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Shadd Family Volume 2, Undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Shadd Family Volume 3, 1855-1960 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Shadd Family Volume 4, Undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Shadd Family Volume 5, Undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Shadd Family (Bearden and Butler), 1975-1978 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Shadd Family - Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Members of the Shadd Family mentioned in the Minutes of the Berean, Undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Series 3: Lineal Information and Charts
  - Baptist Church and the 15th Street Presbyterian Church, Undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Wormley Lineage, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Series 4: Photos
  - Shadd Lineage, Undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Photo - Re: James Wormley, Undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Photo - William H. A. Wormley Family, Undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Photo - William H. A. Wormley Family, Undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Photo - Stanton L. Wormley - Jr. Direct Ancestors, Undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Series 5: Supplemental Volumes
  - Photo - Burruss Family, Undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Wormley Beginnings - Supplement 1, 1192-1843 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Wormley Beginnings - Supplement 2, 1312-1892 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - James Wormley Volume 4, Undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Wormley Family Information Appendix 1, Undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Wormley Family Information Appendix 2, Undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Wormley Family Information Appendix 3, Undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Wormley Family Information Appendix 3, Undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Wormley Family Information Appendix 4, Undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Wormley Family Information Appendix 5, Undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Wormley Property Transactions, 1796-1984 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Lawrence Wormley Property Deeds, 1925-1959 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Wormley Photos Appendix 1, Undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Military Record of James T. Wormley, Undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Gerri Major's Black Society with Doris E. Saunders, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - "Legacy to Buxton", Undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Supplemental Census Information - Wormley Family, 1830-1900 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Index to the Francis L. Cardozo Volumes, Undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Francis L. Cardozo Volume 1, 1837-1903 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Francis L. Cardozo Volume 2, 1837-1903 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Francis L. Cardozo Volume 3, 1837-1903 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Francis L. Cardozo Volume 4, 1837-1903 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Francis L. Cardozo Volume 5, 1837-1903 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Francis L. Cardozo Volume 6, 1837-1903 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Large Documents Volume 1, Undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Large Documents Volume 2, Undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Stanton L. Wormley, Sr. Awards, 1922-1979 (Box 6, Folder 3)